Register of the Charles Hill Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Increment received in 2005 (Box 137)
  - Speeches and writings
    - Discussion on "The Bush Administration Preemption Doctrine and the Future of World Order" with remarks by Charles Hill, 2004
    - Introduction notes, Nick Platt, January 19, 2004
    - "Song of Gu-sta-vra-nis"(Gus Ranis), April 18, 2004
    - Talking points for George Shultz, May 9, 2004
    - Veterans Awareness Day, May 28, 2004
    - Interview, July 12 2004
    - "ICJ 'Advisory Opinion' on the Israeli 'Wall',", July 15, 2004
    - Notes on meeting with Henry Kissinger, George Shultz,Henry Rowan, Charles Hill, July 22, 2004
    - "Commissionism," Wall Street Journal, July 23, 2004
    - "9/11 Commission's Misguided Recommendations on Intelligence," San Diego Union, August 1, 2004 (Box 151)
    - "U.S. Search for Grand Strategy." Orbis, Fall 2004
    - Tiffany Lecture, Wheaton College, October 6, 2004
    - "U.N.: Trying Again to 'Get Serious'," Wall Street Journal, December 7, 2004
    - Reader's report on Churchill, Zionism and the World by Michael Makovsky, January 10, 2005
    - "Two Cultures,", July 11, 2005
  - Subject file
    - Arabists
    - Asia
    - Atlantic partnership
    - Boutros Boutros-Ghali
    - British Petroleum
    - Bryce, James
    - Buddhism
    - Coll, Albert (Box 152)
    - Golder, Frank
    - Gonzalez, Elian
    - Gorbachev, Mikhail
    - Grateful Dead
    - Haiti
    - Holmes, Winifred
    - Hong Kong
    - Iraq
    - Iraq Constitution
    - Jovin, Suzanne
    - Kissinger, Henry
    - Kleinfeld, Joshua
    - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 153)
    - Miscellany
    - National Security Strategy
    - Pacific Security Strategy
    - Picasso, Pablo and Walt Whitman
    - Reagan, Ronald
    - Shultz, George
    - Straus-Hupe, Robert
    - United Nations
      - General
        - Phone list
        - Annual report, 1994
        - Annual report, 1995
      - Africa (Box 154)
      - Boutros Boutros-Ghali – Secretary General
        - "Agenda for Peace"
        - Trip to Washington, D.C.
      - China
      - Early warning
      - Egypt
      - Global development
      - Hebron massacre
      - Human rights
      - Iraq
      - Macedonia
      - Miscellany
      - Najibullah, Mohammed
      - Netherlands
      - Peace-keeping
      - Press club
      - Somalia
      - Tajikistan
      - Waldheim, Kurt
      - Xanadu
    - Vietnam (Notes and research material for course taught by Charles Hill at Stanford University, 1991-92. Hill's folder labels have been retained.) (Box 155)
      - American anarchism
      - Anti-war movement
      - Buddhists
      - Catholicism
      - Cold War
      - Communism
      - Decapitation
      - Dien Bien Phu
      - Dragon ladies
      - Flag
      - Geneva Conference
      - Green Berets
      - Illustrations
      - Imperialism of Japan
      - "JFK" movie
      - Laos
      - Lawrence of Arabia
      - Malraux, Andre
      - Maps
      - Miscellany
      - Ngo Dien Diem
      - "Quiet American"
      - Rousseau, Jean-Jacques
      - Shaplen, Robert
      - Terms
      - Terror (Box 156)
      - Terry and the Pirates
      - Tom Dooley
      - Tonkin Gulf
      - Ugly American
    - Vietnam (Notes and research material for course not taught at Stanford due to departure of Charles Hill for Yale. Hill's folder labels have been retained.)
      - Introduction to course
      - Lecture I
      - Lecture II
      - Lecture III
      - Lecture IV
      - Lecture V (Box 157)
      - Lecture VI
      - Lecture VII
      - Lecture VIII
      - Lecture IX
      - Lecture X
      - Bibliography
      - Book prospectus
      - Research material
        - Cambodia
        - China
        - Domino theory
        - "Embassy Saigon"
        - Histories
        - Images
        - Miscellaneous notes and printed matter
        - Philosophers (Box 158)
        - Press
        - Saigon
        - Sartre, Jean-Paul
        - "Tragedy of American Diplomacy"
        - U.S. Army
        - Vietnam today, 1991
    - Yale University, including material on Grand Strategy
    - Yugoslavia
  - Memorabilia – Intercom box from United Nations Secretary-General's office (Box 159)
  - Phonotapes - "Meaning of Iraq for World Order,", March 24, 2003 (Box 160)
  - Photographs, memorabilia (Box 161)
    - 13 negatives of London, 1956
    - 8 photographs of Norma Thompson
    - 1 photograph of Charles Hill, Debi Graze; 3 photographs of Debi Graze
    - 1 photograph of Boutros Boutros-Ghali
    - 1 photograph of Ellsworth Bunker and other members of the U.S. Mission Council, Vietnam, March 1972
    - 1 photograph of Charles Hill, Phil Habib and others
    - 1 photograph of George W. Bush sent to Norma Thompson
    - 13 photographs of Laura and Christopher Vanlieu, children of Emily Hill, 2002
    - 1 photograph of Emily, Christopher, Laura Vanlieu with Charles Hill and Norma Thompson, June 2004
    - 1 photograph of Emily, Neil, Christopher and Laura Vanlieu, June 2004
    - 3 photographs of Emily, Christopher and Laura Vanlieu in the Father's Day 5K race, June 2004
    - 1 photograph of Charles Hill and others
    - 13 photographs of Charles Hill
    - 2 photographs of Charles Hill, George Shultz and others
    - 2 photographs of Charles Hill, George Shultz, Phil Habib and others
    - 5 photographs of Charles Hill and others
    - 1 photo of Charles Hill, George Shultz, Kiron Skinner; 1 photograph of Charles Hill, Kiron Skinner, and Juanita Nissley at Oakland A's vs. Seattle Mariners baseball game, August 1991
    - 1 photograph of C. Morton Hill (father of Charles)
    - 9 photographs of Brown University crew
    - 2 photographs of Charles Hill and others, Brown University
    - 17 unidentified photographs, Brown University
    - 9 photographs of "Little Prospect," estate of Anthony Nicholas Brady Garvan, Ambler, PA, where Charles Hill worked, 1961-1962
    - 1 photograph of Spiro Agnew; 1 photograph of Henry Kissinger, Ngo Dien Diem, Ellsworth Bunker; 3 photographs of Ellsworth Bunker and others; 1 unidentified photograph – captioned photographs taken in Vietnam, ca. 1971
    - U.S. Department of State certificate and pin to Charles Hill for 30 years of government service, February 1992
    - U.S. Department of State notebook with Secretary of State George Shultz's name inscribed on the cover
    - U.S. Department of State notebook
  - Videotapes - "Can There Be Peace in the Middle East?" Charles Hill and Abraham Sofaer, Uncommon Knowledge, August 10, 1996 (Box 162)
- Increment received in 2007 (Box 163)
  - Biographical file – biographical information on Charles Hill's career
  - Speeches and writings
    - undated
      - Inventory notes – Secretary of State's Library
      - Childhood poems by Charles Hill
      - "Love and War," unpublished manuscript
      - "Emerson"
    - 1991
      - "Longfellow's Dante," "Dante,", May 3
      - "On Language Learning,", September 19
    - drafts for Boutros-Boutros Ghali, 1995-1996
    - "Agenda for Democratization", 1997
    - 1999
      - "Vietnam,", March
      - "History and Politics,", 1999 Fall
    - 2000
      - "The Past, Present and Future of Elian Gonzalez"
      - "A Republic of Taxes?", January
      - "An American Grand Strategy for Russia and China,", January
      - "Negotiations Lite,", April
      - "Edward Gibbon and the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire,", 2000 Fall
      - "Herodotus,", September 11
    - 2001
      - Final Lecture, Directed Studies, April 16
      - Press release for the book "The Age of Terror: America and the World after September 11," Charles Hill co-author, September 15
    - 2002
      - "The Aenid"
      - "Clinton's Legacy: A Lost Decade in Foreign Policy"
      - "Hercules's New Labors"
      - "Literature: The Term in Modern Perspective"
      - "War and the National Character"
      - "The Myth and Reality of Arab Terrorism,", March 5
      - "The Short Story,", 2002 Spring
      - "The New Bush Approach and What to Make of It,", April
      - "An Open Letter to the President,", April 3
      - "Terrorism and the Arab-Islamic World,", May
      - "This Clouded World Has a Silver Lining,", July
      - "Rowing in Other Times, Other Rivers,", August 5
      - "The Middle East: Grand Strategy's Major Challenge,", October
    - 2003 (Box 164)
      - "Milton's Paradise Lost as Grand Strategy,", January 7
      - "History of the World in Six Buildings,", February 3
      - "Who Lost Europe?", February 15
      - "Teach-In," Yale University, March 26
      - "A War to Save the World Order,", March 30
      - "Should New International Entities Be Created?", April
      - "Kissinger as Memoirist," draft, May
      - Lakeside talk, draft for George Shultz, July
      - "The Lessons of History," Canadian Journal of International Affairs, July
      - "A World of Opportunity and a World of Danger" speech for George Shultz, July 10
      - "Journey With Maps: U.S. Task in Liberia,", July 31
    - 2004
      - "Religion: Why It Is Good for America When It Causes Conflict Elsewhere"
      - "What Is Going On? And Where Do We Go From Here?"
      - "Which Is Greatest: Philosophy, History, Political Theory, or Literature?", January 29
      - "American Empire in Literature, Architecture, and Diplomacy," course description, March
      - "The Role of Religion in the Modern World,", March
      - "Dostoevsky's Demons,", April
      - "Panel: The Bush Administration Preemption Doctrine and the Future of World Order," American Society of International Law, April 3
      - "Searching for Grand Strategy,", May
      - "Veterans Awareness Day,", May 28
      - "Hiawatha,", June
      - "Horace, Machiavelli, and Shakespeare: Roman Virtues in Anthony and Cleopatra,", June
      - "What Qualities Enabled the Romans to Become Masters of the Mediterranean World as Demonstrated in the First Pages of Caesar's Gallic War,", June
      - "Shanghai," themes and readings, June 8
      - "The Diplomatic Education of Henry Adams,", July
      - "Gulliver on Governance,", July
      - "Changing Power Centers: The Evolutions of American Alliances and Friendships," interview for Eisenhower Security Conference, July 12
      - "Epics of Grand Strategy,", August (Box 165)
        - Proposal
        - Preface, Introduction, I. The Human Condition
        - II. On the Importance of Untenable Theories
        - III. Elements of Statecraft
        - IV. Getting and Keeping
        - V. Translatio Imperii
        - VI. "In the Beginning All the World Was America"
        - VII. Statecraft
        - VIII. Language Lessons
        - IX. A Sense of Intelligence
        - X. Why Are There Wars?
        - XI. Strategies on the Grand Scale
        - XII. The Pope and the Polis
      - "Keflavik, Ramstein, Clark, Aviano...,", August 24 (Box 166)
      - "Metahistory," course description, September 20
      - "Saddam's Grand Strategy,", October
      - Talking points on North Korea, Iran, Russia, The Power Shift in the East, The Task of Building a Better World Order, Europe, Israel and the Palestinians, Turkey, November
      - "How to Save the U.N. (If We Really Have to),", December 7
      - "Revolution," outline and reading list, December 10
    - 2005
      - Cultural Literacy Test
      - "Aide-Memoir,", January
      - "Edmund Burke,", January
      - "Pope and the Polis," draft, April
      - "Thirtieth Anniversary of the Fall of Saigon,", April
      - "Marx,", April 1
      - "Sigma Phi Epsilon,", April 9
      - Reader's report on Knowing the Enemy: Jihadist Ideology and the War on Terror by Mary Habeck, May
      - "The Rogues Are Losing,", October
      - The Arab Islamic World and the War on Terror, October 6
      - "The New Testament,", November 7
      - "Writing's Place in Statecraft,", November 16
      - "International Ideas and Institutions," course description and book list, November 29
    - 2006
      - Reader's report on The Future of the Bush Doctrine, proposal by Stanley A. Renshon
      - Comments on book proposal, Why Biography Matters – Johnson and Boswell: Their Importance Today, Claude Rawson, editor, February
      - "Architecture of Power,", Spring
      - Review, "MacArthur in the Mideast?" Yale Alumni Magazine, March/April
      - "Splendid Encounters,", March
      - Review, "Complicity with Evil: The United Nations in the Age of Modern Genocide" by Adam LeBor, March 27
      - On Caspar Weinberger, March 29
      - "The U.S. Role in the World," outline, April
      - Remarks on John Gaddis, Courtyard Dedication, Davenport College, Yale University, April 6
      - "Literature of Statecraft," course outline, June 23
- Increments received 2008-2010 (Box 167-169)
- Declassified government records, 1962-1986
  Formerly security-classified records of the British and U.S. governments, released in full or in part. Includes some records determined by the government to be unclassified. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder by country of origin, thereunder by date of creation
  - 2010 October release of U.S. government records, 1966
    Primarily reports on developments in China by an unknown creator; the first page of most reports is absent. Available as PDF files.
  - 2010 December release of British government records, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 170: 1-15)
    Primarily photocopies, with some originals, of communications from the Office of the British Chargé d'Affaires, Peking (Beijing).
  - 2010 December release of U.S. government records, 1962 1986 (Box-folder 170: 16-17)
    Primarily concerns NATO and the United Nations (1962) and negotiations with Australia (1986).
  - 2011 January release of British government records, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 171: 1-5)
    Original and photocopies of communications from the Office of the British Chargé d'Affaires, Peking (Beijing).
  - 2017 release of U.S. government records, 1967-1987
- Increment received in 2013 (Box 172-173)